Guide to the William R. and Erlyn Gould Distinguished Lecture on Technology and the Quality of Life Series video recordings 1992-2006
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
William R. and Erlyn Gould Distinguished Lecture on Technology and the Quality of Life Series video recordings
1992-2006
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A0214
University of Utah
13 VHS videocassettes
The William R. and Erlyn Gould Distinguished Lecture on Technology and the Quality of Life Series video recordings (1992-2006) consist of videos of the annual Gould Lecture delivered at the University of Utah. The Goulds began the lecture in 1992 to meet the "critical need for continuing public education about issues regarding modern technology and its impact on our daily lives."
Historical Note
The official description of the William R. and Erlyn Gould Distinguished Lecture on Technology and the Quality of Life Series states:
"The William R. and Erlyn J. Gould Distinguished Lecture on Technology and the Quality of Life was inaugurated October 7, 1992, at the University of Utah Marriott Library. In establishing the lecture series, Bill and Erlyn Gould both recognized the critical need for continuing public education about issues regarding modern technology and its impact on our daily lives.
Inherent to the advantage of technology is the importance of understanding the ramifications and responsibilities that accompany modern scientific discovery. Only through continuing public education can scientific fact and social philosophy be successfully merged.
The lecture series is intended to provide a forum for the discussion of problems, issues, experiences, and successful case histories of the regeneration and preservation of our communities through the application of modern technology. It is hoped that an increased awareness of obligation in the public trust will emerge among practitioners of technology as they address the very important environmental and life-deteriorating problems facing society today.
Through interaction between technologists and opinion leaders in communities that are the benefactors of their efforts, a synergism can develop through which society may see great benefit in the long-term future. With the lecture series, it is intended that a dialogue be opened between the technologist, the philosopher, the humanist, the private citizen, and all who may wish to assert an active voice in our collective future.
In such an atmosphere of mutual interest and understanding, no one group will be singled out for exclusion or blame for society's ills; rather, through understanding, discourse, and public education the positive direction of our future may be shaped. The Marriott Library's mission is to provide information in all formats sufficient to support the scholarship, teaching, and research programs of the University of Utah to its students and faculty, and to the citizens of the state.
In this light, the annual lecture will strive toward providing a greater public understanding of technology and the social potential that can be cultivated.
In conjunction with the Utah Science, Engineering, and Medical Archives program of the Marriott Library, the lecture series will provide the means of bridging the many disciplines of technology while meeting the needs of the public in understanding its rich and diverse technological heritage.
The William R. and Erlyn Gould Distinguished Lecture on Technology and the Quality of Life Series video recordings (1992-2006) consist of videos of the annual Gould Lecture delivered at the University of Utah.
Materials are arranged chronologically.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
Utah; Lectures and lecturing; Science; Technology; Colleges and Universities; Technology; Science; Moving Images; Moving images
- William R. Gould, 1992 October 07; VHS videocassette (Cassette 1)
  This is the Inaugural lecture in the William R. and Erlyn J. Gould Distinguished Lecture Series. The opening speaker, Greg Thomas, introduces the Gould Lecture Series that will address technology and the quality of life. He mentions that the William R. and Erlyn J. Gould Endowment will support the Marriott Library's Utah Science, Engineering, and Medicine archives as well as general library programs and the lecture series itself. Roger K. Hanson thanks Gould for his support and Arthur K. Smith, President of the University of Utah, addresses the effects of university budget cuts and the importance of private supporters like Gould.
  William Gould explains the purpose of his lecture series and talks about the case history on technology as it applies to the electric industry where he worked most of his life. He also speaks briefly about his wife who passed away recently, recounting how they met and her support in his endeavors. After the speech, he responds to questions from the audience.
  Speakers: William R. Gould; introduction by Greg Thompson (Assistant director of special collections for the Marriott Library), Roger K. Hanson (director of the Marriott Library), Arthur K. Smith (president of the University of Utah)
- Dr. Thomas E. Everhart, 1993 October 07; VHS videocassette (Cassette 2)
  This is the second annual address in the William R. Gould Lecture Series. Greg Thomson gives the introduction and explains the purpose of the lecture series. Dr. Arthur K. Smith introduces the speaker, Thomas S. Everhart who served as president of the California Institute of Technology.
  Everhart discusses how technology evolved and created our industrial society. He explores the history of technology, including advancements such as the TV and the atomic bomb. He also mentions new technology such as virtual reality that is used to teach pilots to fly airplanes and scientific advancements including sequencing the human genome. He explains the Media's ability to determine a nation's will and morality and talks about negative aspects of technology, such as unwanted invasion of privacy and jobs lost from being transferred overseas. The lecture ends with a question and answer session.
  Speakers: Dr. Thomas E. Everhart; introduction by Greg Thompson (Assistant director of special collections for the Marriott Library), Roger K. Hansen (Director of Libraries at the University of Utah), Arthur K. Smith (president of the University of Utah)
- Alan C. Ashton, 1994; VHS videocassette (Cassette 3)
  Greg Thompson welcomes the audience and introduces the topic of the lecture series, technology and the quality of life. Arthur K. Smith introduces the speaker, Alan Ashton, cofounder of WordPerfect.
  Ashton speaks about the success of WordPerfect, beginning with two ideas for computer research projects that he pitched to his professors as a student. The first one accepted was a computer music program that he developed as a graduate. He screens a demonstration of how it worked. Nine years later he finally began development of his second idea, WordPerfect, with a group of graduate students while teaching at BYU. Ashton describes the process of trial and error they underwent and the competition they faced from other companies. Finally, he explains his purpose for creating WordPerfect, gives examples of how it has been beneficial, and argues against the idea that it generates laziness. The lecture concludes with questions from the audience.
  Speakers: Alan C. Ashton; introduction by Greg Thompson (Assistant director of special collections for the Marriott Library), Roger K. Hansen (Director of Libraries at the University of Utah), Arthur K. Smith (president of the University of Utah)
- John Neerhout, 1995 October 05; VHS videocassette (Cassette 5)
  The speaker of this lecture is John Neerhout, Jr., an executive vice president, director, and senior partner of Bechtel Group, Inc. (BGI). In February 1990, Neerhout served in the United Kingdom as project chief executive for Eurotunnel, owner of the Channel Tunnel. In this lecture, Neerhout talks about the history and challenges of the Channel Tunnel transport project, a tunnel that connects Britain and France. According to Neerhout, it is one of the largest private construction projects on record and was dreamed about for over 250 years starting with Napoleon. Diagrams and photographs are shown on the screen to accompany the speech. A short informative video about the Eurotunnel is shown afterwards. Finally, there is a question and answer session.
  Speakers: John Neerhout; introduction by Greg Thompson (Assistant director of special collections for the Marriott Library), Sarah Michalak (Director of Libraries), Arthur K. Smith (president of the University of Utah)
- Introducing Eurotunnel, 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 6)
  This film was shown during John Neerhout's speech at the 4th Gould Lecture, 1995. It is an educational video about Eurotunnel.
- Wayne R. Gould, 1997 October 09; VHS videocassette (Cassette 7)
  The lecture opens with Sarah Michalak who announces that this is the first Gould lecture to be held in the new Gould Auditorium. She talks about the purpose of the Gould lecture series and thanks William Gould and other guests of honor. She announces that William John Gilbert Gould (William R. Gould's father) will speak about his new book, "My Life on the Mountain Railroads" at a later date. Next, President Jerilyn S. McIntyre introduces the speaker Wayne R. Gould who is William and Erlyn's son and an internationally recognized expert in the fields of alternative and renewable energy sources.
  Wayne Gould speaks on alternative energy, focusing on commercial deployment and distribution of renewable resources. He also talks about the role of photovoltaic solar power in developing and industrial nations. There is a question and answer period at the end.
  Speakers: Wayne R. Gould; introduction by Sarah Michalak (Director of the Marriot Library), Jerilyn S. McIntyre (interim President of the University of Utah)
- Dr. Thomas Parke Hughes, 1999 September 22; VHS videocassette (Cassette 8)
  The 8th Annual Gould Lecture is opened by Sarah Michalak who welcomes the audience and honors the members of the Gould family. President Machen introduces the speaker, Thomas Parke Hughes, who is a Mellon Professor Emeritus of the History and Sociology of Science at the University of Pennsylvania and a visiting Professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, The Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm, and Stanford University.
  Hughes then gives his speech titled "Industrial Revolution." He describes the essential technical core, managerial, social, economic, and cultural characteristics of the British and 2nd Industrial Revolution. Then, he compares these industrial revolutions to today's "Information Revolution."
  Speakers: Thomas Parke Hughes; introduction by Sarah Michalak (Director of the Library), J. Bernard Machen (President of the University of Utah
- Christopher R. Johnson, 2000 September 13; VHS videocassette (Cassette 9)
  Sarah Michalak welcomes the audience and the Gould family to the lecture. President Machen introduces the speaker, Christopher R. Johnson, who is an associate professor at the University of Utah School of Computing, directs the Scientific Computing and Imaging Institute and the National Institute of Health Center for Bioelectric Field Modeling Simulation and Visualization, and co-directs the computational science and engineering program.
  Johnson speaks about research in computer simulation and visualization in medicine. He discusses the application of recently developed computing tools in cardiology and neuroscience. These applications allow heart and brain surgeons to use non-invasive diagnostic tools as substitutes for preoperative surgery techniques. Finally, he talks about medical imaging and his vision for the future.
  Speakers: Christopher R. Johnson; introduction by Sarah Michalak (Director of the Library), J. Bernard Machen (President of the University of Utah)
- David W. Eckoff, 2002 September 10; VHS videocassette (Cassette 10)
  This is the 11th annual lecture in the Gould Lecture series. Sarah Michalak gives the introduction and explains the purpose of the lecture series. Next, Bernard Machen introduces speaker David W. Eckoff, former chairman of the University of Utah College of Civil Engineering and a current professor of the college. He is also a nationally recognized water conservationist and was named Engineer of the Year in 1991.
  Eckoff talks about the drought occurring in Utah and throughout the western United States. He gives an analysis of the Hydroelectric cycle in Utah and the Intermountain West and describes drought remedies that include anticipating and preparing, water conservation and Xeriscaping, modified lifestyles, and economic changes. Finally, he explores possible solutions for the drought using technology.
  Speakers: David W. Eckoff; introduction by Sarah Michalak (Director of the Marriot Library), J. Bernard Machen (President of the University of Utah)
- William Wulf, 2003 September 16; VHS videocassette (Cassette 11)
  David Pershing introduces William A. Wulf, the President of the National Academy of Engineering. William Wolf describes the technological challenges facing America as it strives to maintain a leading role in the modern global economy. He urges us to think about the assumptions of what policy tells us we should or shouldn't do. He explains why we should look at the impact of society on technology as opposed to just how technology affects society.
  Speakers: William Wulf; introduced by Sarah Michalak (Director of the Marriot Library), J. Bernard Machen (President of the University of Utah), David Pershing
- David Owens, 2004 September 29; VHS videocassette (Cassette 12)
  Michael K. Young introduces David Owens who is the Executive Vice President of Business Operations for the Edison Electric Institute (EEI).
  Owens describes the state of the nation's electrical power grid. He talks about the debate on how to ensure that consumers get low cost, reliable electricity. This argument that is generally torn between increasing competition in the electric system or providing electricity through vertically integrated utilities. He gives various ways of addressing the challenge and concentrates on three areas: the need for an energy infrastructure, tension between the government Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and the states, and potential solutions for constructing the energy infrastructure. Finally, there is a question and answer period at the end.
  Speakers: David Owens; introduced by Gary Rasmussen, Michael K. Young (President of the University of Utah)
- Clayton M. Christensen, 2006 March 29; VHS videocassette (Cassette 13)
  In the 14th annual Gould Lecture, Clayton M. Christensen speaks about a theory called disruptive innovation that is grounded in research that has revealed how simpler, cheaper, and "good enough" innovations can find application in low-end market tiers and non-consuming customer groups. This presentation introduces the core concepts related to disruptive innovations, showing how they can be both threats and opportunities and explaining what companies can do to encourage disruptive growth.
  Speakers: Clayton M. Christensen